# Héctor Climente González

# Computational biologist & machine learning researcher



# ABOUT ME

"Learn only to be content" - Inscription in Ryōan-ji, Kyōto.

The driving forces of my life are learning and personal growth. I strongly believe in multidisciplinarity and collaboration, and in creating synergies between engineering and basic research, biology and machine learning, academia and the private sector.

#### SELECTED WORK EXPERIENCE

#### Postdoctoral researcher

MAY 2020 - NOW

#### RIKEN AIP

- ▶ Development of machine learning methods for biological problems, including graph-based algorithms and deep learning
- Application of the algorithms above to discover new drug targets of leukemia (transcriptome data) and breast cancer (imaging data)

#### Doctoral researcher

OCT 2016 – APR 2020

Institut Curie & Mines Paris Tech

- ▶ Developed machine learning methods that leverage prior biological knowledge to study the genetics of complex diseases
- ▶ Application of the algorithms above to GWAS, to find both single-SNP associations and epistasis
- ▶ R package *martini* published in Bioconductor, and Python packages *pyHSICLasso* and *spada* in PyPI
- ▶ Conducted internships in Liège University and RIKEN AIP

#### Research assistant

DEC 2013 - AUG 2016

Pompeu Fabra University

▶ Large-scale transcriptome analysis of the functional implications of alternative splicing in cancer

# Head of Biocomputing

SEP 2014 - MAY 2015

Anaxomics Biotech Ltd.

- ▶ Development and maintenance of pipelines for the statistical treatment of omics data
- ▶ Supervision of intern, and collaboration with IT and Data analysis departments regarding database and software maintenance and product deployment

# **EDUCATION**

2016 – 2020

Paris Sciences & Lettres Univ.

2012 – 2014 M.Sc. in Bioinformatics
GPA 9/10
Pompeu Fabra University

Ph.D. in Bioinformatics

2010 – 2013 **B.Sc. in Biochemistry**GPA 8.74/10, 1<sup>st</sup> Class Honors *Barcelona Autonomous Univ.* 

2008 – 2012 **B.Sc. in Biotechnology** GPA 8.58/IO

Barcelona Autonomous Univ.

# SELECTED PUBLICATIONS

Co-author of 10 articles, cited over 400 times.

Climente-González et al. (2020). Boosting GWAS using biological networks: a study on susceptibility to familial breast cancer. PLoS Comp Bio, 17 (3)

Climente-González et al. (2019). Block HSIC Lasso: model-free biomarker detection for ultra-high dimensional data. *Bioinformatics*, 35 (15), i427–i435.

Climente-González *et al.* (2017). The functional impact of alternative splicing in cancer. *Cell reports*, 20 (9), 2215-2226.

#### SELECTED AWARDS

2020 Special Postdoc. Researcher RIKEN 2016 – 2019 PhD EU Fellowship MSCA COFUND

#### LANGUAGES

spanish Native
english Fluent
french Intermediate
Japanese Beginner

# TECHNICAL SKILLS

PROGRAMMING Python, R, C++, Bash

PYTHON pytorch, numpy, pandas, scikit-learn

R tidyverse, igraph, Rcpp

BIG DATA nextflow, HPC (PBS Torque, Slurm),

SQL, Jupyter

оміся GWAS, RNA-Seq (single cell and bulk),

MS-MS proteomics

ML/STATISTICS Graph regularization, statistical

interactions, nonlinear association

deep learning

DEVOPS Docker, conda, unit testing, continuous

integration, git

# SOFT SKILLS

- ▶ Experienced **communicator**: talks in international conferences, lead writer of articles and grant proposals, imparted workshops on reproducible research
- ▶ **Project management** in teams and singleperson projects, **mentoring**, and coordination of **international collaborations**
- ▶ **Organization** of summer school on breast cancer, **teaching** assistant in large scale machine learning course
- ▶ Courses on critical thinking, ethics, project management, theater, and mindfulness